[SPEAKER_02]: So, this is the Sabha Sutta.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Blessed One said, what is the All?
[SPEAKER_02]: Simply the I and forms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ear and sounds.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nose and smells.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tongue, flavor.
[SPEAKER_02]: Body and touches.
[SPEAKER_02]: And mano and dhammas.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, mano... Intellect.
[SPEAKER_02]: Intellect, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And dhammas, images...
[SPEAKER_02]: Images, phenomena.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thoughts, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, intellect and thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: This, monks, is called the all.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anyone who would say, rejecting this all, I will make known another.
[SPEAKER_02]: All.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: A new all.
[SPEAKER_02]: I will describe another one.
[SPEAKER_04]: Something... A higher reality than this.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: If questioned on what exactly might be the grounds for your statement, he would be unable to explain and furthermore get frustrated.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that is not his domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not his personal scope.
[SPEAKER_02]: He cannot know that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, whatever that new or old he might be describing, it will be within any one of those.
[SPEAKER_04]: Cannot be anything apart from the sixth sense base.
[SPEAKER_04]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, you say, no, no, this is apart from it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you're just describing another image to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is part of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can describe another, or all that I... that you believe.
[SPEAKER_04]: You believe in, imagine.
[SPEAKER_04]: Ignoring the fact that, exactly, you imagine it.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's real as imagination, sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: As images, as phenomena, it is real.
[SPEAKER_04]: And thus, it's very much within this all.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you claiming that it's beyond the six senses, while using the six senses to describe it and refer to it, or even just think of it,
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that's a contradiction in terms for that very reason.
[SPEAKER_04]: How can you then designate the all, if you can't even think it?
[SPEAKER_03]: What are you designating?
[SPEAKER_03]: What are you talking about?
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what people say, like, well, you know, you can't... you can't really describe God.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like, well, you just described it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's exactly a description.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, it's indescribable.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, that's a property of God, which is then describable.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then it's a contradiction in terms, such a statement.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, here we got that, that common view, which is, there is something beyond all the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, that ground of being, that unity of... Self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unity of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: With a higher self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That, yeah, one, non, non-dual, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_02]: Consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: It never changes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: All the names you can...
[SPEAKER_02]: But how do you know that?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you have images of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I have a thought about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which are changing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I'm still stuck.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you're ignoring what's right in front of you and reinterpreting everything from this internal, obviously, you cannot be outside of your aggregates, but externally assumed universe and world and point of view.
[SPEAKER_04]: And in a nutshell, that's the definition of attavāda.
[SPEAKER_04]: Assuming that you can be out, don't matter what view you have, what interpretation, what description, whether you're talking about anicca or the universal ātman, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_04]: If there is an attitude of... from the outside, that's attavāda.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you don't think necessarily in terms of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unique, independent... Means, basically, outside point of view.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's an internal image.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which you realize, oh, that's why it's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, whenever you think outside, it's done with mano and intellect, which is six sense bases, which means it's inside of this all.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, is there a thing beyond the aggregates or beyond experience?
[SPEAKER_02]: And you just answer, no, there's nothing like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, no, see, that's already... there's nothing.
[SPEAKER_04]: You just made it into something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Theoretically, there is nothing, but you have to realize that, like, theory, it's always going to be on a level of review.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you can have the right theory, but even then, it will remain on the level of review, which means
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not true for you.
[SPEAKER_04]: You need to start doing it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, when you make a...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I must never make a statement there is nothing.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: Make a statement there is nothing, but then include it rightly in the all that is here and now.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is your practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is your bhāvana.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is your right all that... That is your doing.
[SPEAKER_04]: ...right contradiction... your right... rightly arranged things that will be then freeing you from these contradictions.
[SPEAKER_04]: Assumptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Every assumption is... has to be a contradiction in itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not that you necessarily see it that way initially, but that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_04]: Assumption of external self, assumption of the views coming, like, as the determining factor for everything else, ignoring the reality upon which they exist.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I can have an imagination, a fantastic imagination of consciousness, some light or whatever, some image of the ground of being or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I can just devote myself to that and abandon all of this lesser stuff.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Lesser consciousnesses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, you know, get quite far and
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Supposedly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, if you really commit to it, again, not to the image, necessarily.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, image on its own will not free you from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if on account of that image, even if it's to to some extent contradictory, you do start living withdrawn from the senses, in the solitude, contemplating lack of satisfaction, then you will abandon sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even without the right view, even without the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: But not without the work.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because there's a difference between abandoning sensuality and replacing it with a higher reward.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not abandoning.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you see, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what I'm saying is, it is possible to actually abandon sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: The Buddha said it in the suttas as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: You cannot prove the assumption of sensuality, undo that contradiction, even outside of the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the work needs to be done, not like on account of some divine kind of providence,
[SPEAKER_04]: descending upon you, and suddenly you're just free.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, if monks and nuns, or practices, other practices, samanas, ibrāmins of other religions, freed themselves from sensuality, it had to have been the same way of gradual training, unintentionally, withdrawal, guarding of the sense door, living in the seclusion, and really experiencing that self-loathing on the level of the presence of the body and the aggregates, that they do not want.
[SPEAKER_04]: But not act out of it, to destroy it, or go back to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now, sure, they might have had all sorts of other views.
[SPEAKER_04]: They would then not necessarily make them value it the way they should, but factually, they could have uprooted the sensual desire, the assumption of beautiful in the senses and in the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, a person can still have, like, the love of God.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But they would have, they could have, if they applied, if they actually endured, withdrew from the senses, from the unwholesome states, completely relinquishing any perception of form that they have, as in relinquish the ownership and delight in it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: They could have experienced the release on account of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because the mind has been developed in regard to their own body.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's like when the Buddha said that he wasn't perfectly celibate, you know, until he gave up even the... Well, from the dhamma point of view now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But he gave up sensuality, sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: But he extended that for the future rebirths.
[SPEAKER_04]: See, you gave up sensuality here, you haven't... you're not free from saṃsāra, which means you can go back to, like, whatever, heavenly rebirths, but when that runs out,
[SPEAKER_04]: You're back to sensuality and back to other things.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah, you want to be perfectly celibate, perfectly withdrawn, as in never even return to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Doesn't matter how many eons ahead you might spend in the heavens.
[SPEAKER_04]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_04]: You never return to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: But for that, you need the right view.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_04]: The person free from sensuality, with the right view, is anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_04]: And he's called non-returner for that very reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the thing that distinguishes somebody who's given up sensuality with attavada and somebody who's given up attavada...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we were talking about images and dhammas...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you were saying, like, somebody might give up sensuality on account of some image of a god, or that they were devoted to, that they valued more than sensuality, or... Again, that's not giving up, though.
[SPEAKER_04]: They might be... That's replacing it with... Yeah, yeah, that's more like you just replace one intoxication with another.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so it's not... Yeah, yeah, that's not it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what I'm saying is, and the Buddha himself said that, when people ask him how, what do we practice in order to be reborn in Brahma world, or to see the heavens,
[SPEAKER_04]: And it was, well, you practice perfect, sort of, celibacy, not giving in to sensual thoughts and so on, and these heavens will be guaranteed for you.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know which heavens specifically, but that was kind of the gist of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: The point being, yes, there is that mundane, sort of, you just replace one intoxication with another.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's not uprooting sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: But somebody can, on account of their belief in the view in God or Atman or whatever, actually do the work on the physical level.
[SPEAKER_04]: And keep the precepts, be completely withdrawn from the sensuality, guard of the sense doors, live in seclusion, experience that, as I call it, existential patiga of the senses there, that are now being withdrawn and tamed.
[SPEAKER_04]: Basically, go through withdrawals.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's that self-loathing in that practice sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: The mind will have to come down if they don't give it up.
[SPEAKER_04]: And when the mind comes down, they will then realize, oh, you know, this is actually more valuable, this is safer, this is more peaceful, this is less disturbing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, central pursuits.
[SPEAKER_04]: And factually, lose desire towards central pleasures.
[SPEAKER_04]: Free... we're free from that assumption that they are actually pleasant, that these burning charcoal embers are pleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: Without, still on the basis of that wrong notion of the eternal self or whatever, but not, oh, on account of an image, they give it up.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: On account of an image, they might actually do the work, and it's the work that will free them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's implicit anyway, this idea of...
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why I always ask people, I ask you as well, like, oh, how did you start?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you know, what was your first...
[SPEAKER_04]: But, I mean, it doesn't apply just to other practices and religions.
[SPEAKER_04]: It applies to even Buddhist practices today.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was like, sure, whatever instruction do you follow, whether it's for jhāna or for this or for that, whoever instructed you, wherever you learned it from, did it emphasize
[SPEAKER_04]: The necessity of gradual training, of withdrawal, of guarding of the senses, of taming of the mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you realize that 99% think, no, it goes straight into the view, straight into the images, straight into the pictures, and this is what it is, and this is what it will be.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then you just, okay, I'll just go straight there, because that's what I'm presented here.
[SPEAKER_04]: So often you will be like...
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, yeah, it's great.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, yeah, is this virtue and precepts?
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, we should just talk about it, but... No, yeah, I understand this.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, yeah, the jhāna and this.
[SPEAKER_04]: Great.
[SPEAKER_04]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'll just go straight there.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, people completely neglect and ignore, or put aside, or do it kind of second best, kind of as an afterthought, the precepts and guarding of the sense doors, and they think their commitment to a view, their image, the information, is how you progress.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, you can have, literally, you can have the image of some random deity, but if you do the work on account of it, you'll be free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then you realize, oh, but that's why I'm free.
[SPEAKER_04]: You still might have your beliefs and your deities and so on, but you will know where the freedom came from.
[SPEAKER_04]: You will know where the drying up and taming of the senses came from.
[SPEAKER_03]: Might as well skip the deity and say just this.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, then, I think you would obviously be much... in a much more favorable position to re-evaluate your beliefs and your deities, because you're not being obstructed by sensual desires and projections.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why even somebody with the wrong view, who has went through like guarding of the sense door and not giving it up, keeping the precepts, they actually factually have diminished the amount of dust in their eyes.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, when then they would hear the Buddha, they would be, oh, wow, but that's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because they already have the ingredients for it, more or less.
[SPEAKER_04]: They're already there, in a sense of... their perspective is seriously unpolluted now, because they have withdrawn from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: And they were.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, the fire worshippers, the whatever else, the 500 disciples, when they came, and then completely different practices, but they were obviously tamed, physically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Their senses were properly developed.
[SPEAKER_04]: The mind was developed in regard to the senses.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, although it was a completely different view of what the practice is and what the value is, when they heard the Buddha, they all, oh, okay, let us all become monks now.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is it.
[SPEAKER_04]: They understood it instantaneously.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that is against the background of India being generally quite valuing asceticism.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if we see, like, the deities and the practices, the way they are presented nowadays,
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it seems to me that is quite different.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, this is useful to make the distinction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_04]: The reason they understood it, it's not because their deities made them understand completely different practice that negates those deities.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was because their deities, whatever, they still actually practiced withdrawal from the senses.
[SPEAKER_04]: They were they were celibate, they were taming, guarding of the sense doors, the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: The mind will have to clean up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, whatever teaching do you follow,
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, ask yourself, okay, but does it go straight into the images, the view, the expectations, the pleasure, the joy, the joy, the happiness, the jhāna, the jhāna?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, you read the suttas for that jhāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: Do you do everything else beforehand?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or do you just go straight to the pity, just the pity?
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just everything is just blissful, because that's what my meditation is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that's not the meditation that the Buddha was talking about, ever.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, bliss will come, but obviously of a very different kind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, again, even if you say, well, I don't, I don't believe in any of that.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't, I don't think it's necessary.
[SPEAKER_04]: I just have the view or the instruction and it works for me.
[SPEAKER_04]: What, what do you have to lose if you keep the precepts and guard the sense doors?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you don't have to.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not asking you to give up whatever view.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not saying all these views are wrong or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, just objectively, rationally, what do you have to lose?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, the pleasure that I talked of in the census... Oh, you mean the pleasure opposite of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: You still don't want to give up while you want the pleasure of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like, oh, yeah, what do I have to lose if I'm... if I actually do follow what they should say?
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't need to give up my...
[SPEAKER_04]: Jhāna practice, or whatever else, but... yeah, why don't I take the precepts seriously, be celibate, guard the sense doors, live with...
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, I can then have a like a... Jhāna on steroids.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, you know, if I obviously have a view that I can have jhāna while I'm steeped in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Imagine the jhāna that the Buddha was talking about.
[SPEAKER_04]: The jhāna when you're withdrawn from everything unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, there you go.
[SPEAKER_04]: Use your sensual desire for your jhāna and actually do it properly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Do it the proper way.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, is there a practical way to discern the all?
[SPEAKER_03]: Without making the wrong move of trying to look at it from outside.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, how is the door being... Rather, there is a practical way, but not without making a move from the outside.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly, that's the point.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's learning how to correctly recollect in regard to the move from the outside that you already made.
[SPEAKER_04]: In other words, learning how to include what you excluded.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is how you discern from... That is how you will eventually find the balance and stop spilling outside for a standpoint.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it's it's it's a it's a it's a it's a like a training process of training your mind to that spillage of outside view, reflexively re-include it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But obviously, you're going to re-include it too much.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then that will become your outside view.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then you include that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you do it for as long as the mind doesn't calm down within that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's almost a description of developing yoniso, manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's exactly what it is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whose description?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, what we were talking about the other day.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ah, my description, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: I thought, oh, who described that?
[SPEAKER_04]: That's a good description.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, that's exactly what it is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yoniso, manasikāra, that's exactly what it is.
[SPEAKER_04]: That being able to establish that balance which
[SPEAKER_04]: Again, whoever tries it, they're gonna try and establish it from that standpoint.
[SPEAKER_04]: It won't be the balance.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, you include a standpoint.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, that's already temporary balance.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, you exclude.
[SPEAKER_04]: You again assume the external point of view, or this is it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You include that.
[SPEAKER_04]: To that extent, there is a balance.
[SPEAKER_04]: Up until the balance remains.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whether you include or exclude, the balance remains.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's where you know, like, okay, yeah, so I stopped assuming outside.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because even the thoughts of outside, it's just I cannot doubt that they're not outside.
[SPEAKER_04]: And even saying that there is not outside, I cannot even imply that there could be some other outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Any thought, any images understood in its own nature, is being there, inside, for what it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: That has to result in the Noble Right View, which is precisely the seeing, well, the uprooting of the Atavada.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, when there is no more,
[SPEAKER_04]: When you're incapable of... You can have thoughts of outside, but they don't carry the same assumption, the weight of actually being outside.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not following them.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just an image.
[SPEAKER_04]: You still see there's an image of outside, so it's like a relative outside.
[SPEAKER_04]: There is no belief behind that it's an outside of this whole thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, yeah, then there is no more ātvāda.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly why that person could also become incapable
[SPEAKER_04]: Depending on what is perceived as an outside form, duty, necessity.
[SPEAKER_04]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_04]: They cannot even conceive that as relevant anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because they're not out there anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: There is no more atavāda, so there is no more... You know, like how people take the weight of tradition for granted.
[SPEAKER_04]: Many do it, thus it's right, thus it must be done.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is sīla bhattabhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a public view.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a view of that public world where value comes by always doing it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that one, free from attavāda, is incapable of thinking that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what is it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Roam alone like a rhinoceros horn.
[SPEAKER_04]: I've gone beyond the witherings of the view, that verse.
[SPEAKER_04]: Nobody can be my guide.
[SPEAKER_04]: Roam alone like a rhinoceros horn.
[SPEAKER_04]: As in Sotāpanna, who has understood, it's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not like nobody can be my guide, I'm the best.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, it's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, see, others are perceived as the external selves to my external ātavāda already.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if that fundamental ātavāda is gone, the external selves of other people is also gone.
[SPEAKER_04]: The external extent of their selves, let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the weight of a million people doing something is meaningless.
[SPEAKER_04]: You will do it because it's aligned with the dhamma, or not aligned with the dhamma, you won't do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's equally within, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sensuality, ill-will, distraction, cause one to to lose that perspective acting out of these things, because...
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, acting out causes one to lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I mean, they're there, and you don't act out of them, then you're seeing them for what they are, so that you're not losing perspective.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, they might still be arising for somebody who is not free from them, but you realize that that's, in and of itself, it's not an impediment.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, what is an impediment is when you wrongly attend to it, act out of it, try to get rid of it, are averse towards it, or delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's that's what's going to maintain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can sort of, yeah, have a mood there, and if you're not acting out of it, you're you're seeing it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then it's kind of all right.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like, yeah, I mean... Well, it came on its own, it will go on its own.
[SPEAKER_04]: You realize, oh, this is...
[SPEAKER_04]: My responsibility, this is the line for it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I won't delight, I won't ignore it, I won't be averse towards it, I won't act out of it, but that's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, if I feel entitled for it to not be here, oh, I am...
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm involved with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which means my mind is not turned away from these things, because I still feel the need, the necessity to deal with it, crossing that line.
[SPEAKER_04]: As I get a simile of going out, chasing people that are in front of the... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm safe in here.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm safe behind this line.
[SPEAKER_03]: It cannot come in here.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're eternally calm.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: With the turtle, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_04]: The turtle retracting its limbs until the jackal kind of leaves.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not like, you know, doing kung fu moves on it to beat the jackal up so the jackal leaves.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, it's just...
[SPEAKER_04]: I can stay like this.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then jackal will have to lose interest and go.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's when we speak about this endurance, endurance.
[SPEAKER_04]: People seem to... some people seem to conflate that with bearing.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, they translate it as enduring, but the Pāli's... bahatabhā...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's what... it means bearing, means bearing of the elements.
[SPEAKER_04]: People sometimes tend to confuse when we talk about enduring for bearing, which is at bahatabhā, the Pāli word.
[SPEAKER_04]: When we say enduring, it's really word khanthi, patience.
[SPEAKER_04]: It always goes patient endurance.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the reason why I avoid patience is because, oh yeah, be patient, just be patient, just...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like, well, yeah, sure, but really think about what that means.
[SPEAKER_04]: That means, when I'm pressured by sensual desire, do I get rid of it, because I'm impatient, or can I endure it patiently, and not act out, and not cross the line?
[SPEAKER_04]: Does the turtle... What happens to the turtle if it gets impatient with the jackal that's still not leaving?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's gonna have its arms snapped out, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, so, when I say enduring, for, I don't know, for new listeners or for people that are still doubtful about it, take that to mean khanti in the suttas, patience.
[SPEAKER_04]: And patient endurance is the highest purification, as Buddha says, the highest tapas.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't mean pahatābhā of just bear it, just bear the elements, just bear the central thought, just bear... Or fight against it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that's it's already a form of fighting against.
[SPEAKER_04]: You need khanti to do pahatābhā.
[SPEAKER_04]: You need khanti to bear elements.
[SPEAKER_04]: You need to be patient.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, basically, any of these sabhās, savasūtā, you need khanti for.
[SPEAKER_04]: For development, for abandoning, for avoiding.
[SPEAKER_04]: You need to be patient first.
[SPEAKER_04]: To discern, like for hindrances, as we spoke before, when hindrances arise, sensuality or real will, if you're habitual, I get rid of this, I think the opposite, I do this, I do that, you're not very patient, aren't you?
[SPEAKER_04]: What's the problem of...
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not welcoming this.
[SPEAKER_04]: I didn't make it arise.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why do I need to do the work of removing it, making it go away?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I'll just be patient and let it go away.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when it sees that I'm not reaching out and interfering, means it's going to lose interest in me.
[SPEAKER_04]: See, if I come to provoke you, you could be... or get a reaction, I don't care what type of reaction it's going to be.
[SPEAKER_04]: Mahārāja doesn't care whether you're going to like him or hate him, as long as you give him a reaction.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly every time... there was exactly the description for every time in the suttas when Mahārāja was there tempting.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm trying, I've been trying for six, seven years following him like like a crow just to pick on a piece of fat that dropped out or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's nothing, nothing left for me to grab on.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, so he left him alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the only way Mara has of remaining unseen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because... Well, that's the only way Mara has power over you.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you react.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you go out in his domain.
[SPEAKER_04]: He said that.
[SPEAKER_04]: The Buddha said that.
[SPEAKER_04]: He says Mara does with people what he wants because people take what belongs to Mara.
[SPEAKER_04]: They go there in Mara's domain.
[SPEAKER_04]: What are the things that belong to Mara?
[SPEAKER_04]: The all.
[SPEAKER_04]: The all belongs to Māra.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you react, act, interfere, engage with the all, Māra controls you to that extent, because you are the one who took what doesn't belong to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, if you're patient, or you practice this endurance, then it's possible to then discern the nature of
[SPEAKER_01]: That image or that phenomena.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's enduring.
[SPEAKER_04]: Having said that, I think, since we qualified that when we say endurance, we mean khanti, and people tend to confuse that for bearing of pahātava, it can be other way around as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sometimes people say, oh, this is the khanti of endurance by simply bearing random things and expecting them to go away.
[SPEAKER_04]: See, expecting things to go away means you're still impatient.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you're enduring things on physical level, you're bearing things on physical level, you might not be acting out, but mentally, you're not patient.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not accepting the fact that there ever is an enduring.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're still trying to get rid of them.
[SPEAKER_04]: And now you're using patience as a wishful thinking that it will go away on its own.
[SPEAKER_04]: It will go away on its own.
[SPEAKER_04]: But see, you leaning towards it going away means you're not truly patient.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not truly equanimous towards this thing, whether it's here or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: I am safe with my limbs retract.
[SPEAKER_04]: I am not bothered with the fact that there is an angry person threatening and shouting at me through this door.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because I have understood now that he cannot cross this line.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I understood that because I've been patient sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_04]: I endured things on the right level sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: The sign of you, that you're doing it right, it's always in the suttas that it says, his mind is elevated, and he's internally calm.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: With that thing in front of him there, with that monster there, his mind is elevated and internally calm.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that becomes your measure of the calmness.
[SPEAKER_04]: The fact that I didn't have to get rid of this thing, which I used to always think it was bothered and I couldn't go to sleep if it was there.
[SPEAKER_04]: All day, not bothering me.
[SPEAKER_04]: The fact it was there was bothering me.
[SPEAKER_04]: I was bothering myself with the thought of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now, that has not changed.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yet, I am unbothered.
[SPEAKER_04]: Completely unbothered.
[SPEAKER_02]: Amongst things that used to bother me.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Amongst suffering, he ceases to suffer.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's that whole, like, the element, the kāgata, the one-pointedness, it just means higher place, unified higher place, safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the river being torched by a flaming torch, like, it's completely unaffected by... or the earth being... Oh, yeah, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whatever rubbish is thrown on the earth, it just cannot make a difference.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whether the wind blows over feces or rubbish, it makes no difference to the wind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's... and it's also like peripheral awareness with this thing in front of you.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's... yeah, that's kind of that direction.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's... that's... that's where your shell is, the turtle.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you gotta have to learn then... you have to start discerning these subtler things.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, first physically and verbally is the way of acting out and reaching towards the jackal.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, do you cultivate the mind of... oh, I'm not acting towards sensuality, but mentally I'm happy about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, you're not enduring it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're already welcomed it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or, I'm not acting towards this aversive thing that's in front of me, but I really wish it harm.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like, oh, again, you're not enduring on the right level.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're now averse.
[SPEAKER_04]: Either way, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, body, speech and mind need to be not acted out of.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you discern that right, where the line is, that khanti is the highest tapas, is the highest purification, that endurance on the right level, that I keep saying, then you realize, okay, yeah, that is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Protect that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Don't lose sight of it, the balance of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And whatever comes, sensuality, ill-will, any of the hindrances, you will see through them.
[SPEAKER_04]: And they will not hinder you to the... to whatever extent they might have arisen, it won't be hindering.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because they only hinder you when you step, when you cross the line, when you went there, when you got involved by body, speech or mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: To go back to the sutta about the all, about the I and forms, the ear and sounds and manner, the intellect and dhammas, so it's only possible really to to discern this relationship
[SPEAKER_01]: If if one is secluded from sensuality, or will, because the... yeah, if one is involved in particular sounds, or particular sights, or particular phenomena... And that seclusion might start by being physically withdrawn,
[SPEAKER_04]: Keeping the precepts, guiding of the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, that seclusion is really developed, when once you're physically withdrawn, you have your mind revolving around unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not averse towards it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not welcoming it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're actually patiently enduring those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, thoughts of sensuality, I must get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I must not act towards it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why do I want to get rid of it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because I'm averse to the pain that it puts on me.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I'm not patient.
[SPEAKER_04]: If there is aversion, you're not patient.
[SPEAKER_04]: If there is lust, there's no patience.
[SPEAKER_04]: If there is distraction, there is no patience.
[SPEAKER_04]: There is no endurance on the right level.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the reason why I keep kind of hammering this in is because a person might think, okay, yeah, so withdrawn from these things means I stop, I stop, obviously keep precepts, I stop acting out, then I go into seclusion and I stop thinking about these things and it will just fall off, fall... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: That line is discerned when you have, sure, withdrawn yourself physically from the water, but then mentally, you actually realize, okay, but I have no say in mano and its own dhammas.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the same sense, I have no say in eyes, in... in the sights, except restraint.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, how do you restrain the mind?
[SPEAKER_04]: How do you make mind not think images, which... when that's another image?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's why it's much harder, as the Buddha said, to... to see this mind as not yours, and to experience this passion towards it, than other things that are inferior, that are more kind of coarser, because, yeah, you've been adhering to it, you've been confusing it for your own, and so on, for so long.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's where that line is.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, once you have kept the precepts, are keeping the precepts, are withdrawn, living in seclusion, the mind will then come up with stuff, come up with...
[SPEAKER_04]: Upsets, desires, things like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you deal with them, not by further taking your mind out of it and trying to stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_04]: You deal with it by discerning the line for that jackal that is trying to get you involved.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which means, initially, you're going to be involved and it's going to be unpleasant and you will want to act out of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you want to go and resolve it or practice nostril concentration to stop thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: All of that because you're truly impatient.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it's like, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: I have been withdrawn physically.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm guarding my sense doors.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not breaking the precepts.
[SPEAKER_04]: The virtue has been established, accomplished in.
[SPEAKER_04]: I can take this pain of mind just revolving around stuff.
[SPEAKER_04]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: Let him revolve.
[SPEAKER_04]: It will have to...
[SPEAKER_04]: Elephant from the jungle, pin down.
[SPEAKER_04]: Do you think he's just going to immediately...
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, let's let's discuss what you want to train me.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm fully pliable right from the start.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's gonna try to break and kick and scream and kill you.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it's like, well, no matter how much it hurts, you know.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: I pin him down.
[SPEAKER_04]: He can't break this.
[SPEAKER_04]: If I don't choose to let him out, he can't harm me.
[SPEAKER_04]: If I don't choose to go back to sensuality, this mind, doesn't matter how many days... And that's why I say, like, often, you have to, at least initially, when you say, oh, I'll endure things on the right level, you have to accept the worst possible scenario.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because the mind will come up, yeah, but if I don't resolve this doubt, but if I don't resolve this upset, forever it will be like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm ready to endure it infinitely.
[SPEAKER_04]: On that level, I shall not ever again cross the line and interfere with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I don't transmute this sexual energy, my head's gonna explode or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: I will still not let the elephant go free.
[SPEAKER_04]: Until it actually calms down.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because all of these are tricks and traps of a jackal trying to get out.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but I'll stay here forever.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, I better start running.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, got me again.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it is that fear.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even minor things, when you're in seclusion, minor things will be little doubts.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or, hmm, he said... Did he mean this?
[SPEAKER_04]: Did he mean... Three days later...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's still there.
[SPEAKER_04]: He meant that, and... And now, now I know everything else that would have followed, which never happened.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then you realize, oh, then you go and talk to that person, and he never meant that, and now it's all fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, it's not.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's fine in a worldly sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: In an internal sense, you acted out.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you use the the reference of the jackal and the world for where your safety is.
[SPEAKER_04]: And there was a mistake.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now it's going to come back again.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, basically, you let the elephant go.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, now you're going to start again.
[SPEAKER_01]: By acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: By acting out of it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what you want to do is recognize that such thoughts will inevitably be amplified in solitude.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you have to accept the fact that, as I said, infinitely I will
[SPEAKER_04]: Endure this patiently, in that true sense of the word, on the right level, and not act out of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's my sole job.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not to cross this line.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not to open this door.
[SPEAKER_04]: And if you have set it up through physical withdrawal of the precepts, guarding of the sense doors, obviously the speech, physical withdrawal from company, seclusion, doesn't matter how much your mind will doubt and all the other hindrances, it will have to come down.
[SPEAKER_04]: And again, that's why view is important.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you don't see, if you don't... if you haven't taken a faith that it will have to come down, if you don't necessarily haven't seen it before, you won't do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because there is no immediate verification.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just... Well, immediate verification is it's getting worse.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, this elephant was not this angry when I caught it, but now it's like a different beast.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, yeah, that's kind of the point.
[SPEAKER_04]: But doesn't matter the anger of the jackal.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're going to start developing confidence in the safety of your shell, of not crossing the line.
[SPEAKER_04]: Once you have stopped crossing the line, then you realize, oh, OK, yeah, actually.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then it will become self-evident.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was just going to say, the two factors for the arising of Right View is exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The right teaching, the right faith in the teaching, and then attending to the all correctly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And putting, like, doing it, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Repeating it, cultivating it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Cultivating it, and if the teaching is well expounded,
[SPEAKER_04]: As it says in the suttas, as in, no relevant path or the order of development is left out.
[SPEAKER_04]: See, the teaching is not well expounded.
[SPEAKER_04]: If, as we said, one of the first with this group things we started doing, and I said, what would you say if somebody asked her, how to free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_04]: And you answered, well, you know, anatta, by not taking self and stuff.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's true, but it's not well expounded.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because now, they would just leave with that view, thinking that's all I have to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And they might do it practically, but literally, they're building the sixth floor, when they have no other floors below that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it just won't work.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's like the gradual training and the development that would then bring this endurance on the right level, this khanti, to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you see these principles in concrete...
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you're experiencing concrete safety now.
[SPEAKER_04]: See, I haven't.
[SPEAKER_04]: I got rid of this mind, or distracted myself, or acted towards sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yet, it stopped bothering me, because I simply didn't allow acting out towards it.
[SPEAKER_04]: I didn't try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, as I said, yeah, you might feel like, I have to do this forever.
[SPEAKER_04]: I have to endure this nuisance so close to home, forever.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like, yeah, so close to home, that's not yours.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then you realize, oh, so I have no right to not to complain about it, because this doesn't belong to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: In terms of this all again, you've got I and forms, or sense objects, and that the bodily senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, these two domains, I and the forms.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I'm seeing forms.
[SPEAKER_02]: And where's the I?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you've got to find, and we were speaking about earlier today, so there's these two domains, and one must be sort of counter-measured by the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if I'm just out into the senses, sense objects, sorry, then there's this
[SPEAKER_02]: It's...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm tipped over.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's no balance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when you countermeasure that counterweight...
[SPEAKER_04]: When you know how to look at it, you'll see the other end of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, where's the eye?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, so you've got these two domains, and there's, as I found today in this assembly of scales, you countermeasure, and then there's that sama.
[SPEAKER_02]: He applies this, and he finds that balance, and then he strives for that, to keep that balance.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's already fully based on yonisumnasikāra.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what that balance is.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what yonisumnasikāra is.
[SPEAKER_04]: See, manasikāra is what you attend to the front.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's generally.
[SPEAKER_04]: Every manasikāra is ayoniso.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not aware of its counterweight.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not aware of its womb, or where it came from, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_04]: What is the opposite to this?
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not aware of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yoniso manasikāra, it's not a different way of attending to something new.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just learning how to not overly attend, so to speak, towards objects and discern the background in regard to them at the same time.
[SPEAKER_04]: And what else?
[SPEAKER_04]: That's exactly similar to the scale.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's at the same time, it's even.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not too much, not too little.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not to replace another thing, a new scale, another thing in front of you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Doesn't matter what you put in the front, whether it's a different thing, the weight of it, that's what matters.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, how much you've committed to it through your careless attention.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, all these translations of yoniso,
[SPEAKER_04]: You can take them one way or the other, but they need to be qualified, because, obviously, it's one of the most... well, it's the origin of practice, really.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a person who doesn't know how to balance their attention.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I don't mean anything mystical by that.
[SPEAKER_04]: I simply mean, like, seeing what else is simultaneously there, present as a background, as the root, as the womb of this attention, whatever I'm attending to.
[SPEAKER_04]: They won't have any any balance to work on.
[SPEAKER_04]: They won't have any recognition of what the middle way is.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, for that new book that I'm working on, I started translating yoniso manasikāra as, how do you say?
[SPEAKER_04]: Concurrent.
[SPEAKER_04]: Attending concurrently, or concurrent attention.
[SPEAKER_04]: Simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_04]: Concurrent.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah, I'm attending to this.
[SPEAKER_04]: At the same time, the experience of the all of attending to this, the image of it, that is a background image, that is a context, is seen, which is what gives this direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I spent years practicing this meditation, where it was like, okay, something has arisen, let's say, some kind of, yeah, angry thinking, like before, and now, okay, I've got to just move my attention away to the breath, to the sensations of the body.
[SPEAKER_04]: Distract yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what this is saying is, yeah, exactly, like, to not get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you get rid of it, you're not going to find the balance in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You won't find that line I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly that sutta, that... about the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_04]: All of the five hindrances are abandoned, not by replacing them with this or that, but with yoniso, manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, every every hindrance is an imbalance in itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: You balance them out by attending to the womb of them.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it gives the examples, like the hindrance of sensuality arises, he attends correctly to that weight of that beautiful, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_04]: And he ceased to be hindered by it.
[SPEAKER_04]: It remains there on a scale.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not his problem anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: Aversion, the the weight of the repulsive, the weight of unenergetic, the weight of agitated, the weight of uncertainty, does not necessarily need to become a hindrance of a doubt, if you don't lose the sight of its counterweight, basically, the other end of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, in a way, like, seeing it as something, rather than being pulled by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, seeing ill-will as ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a thing, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That too.
[SPEAKER_04]: Recognizing it as a thing there, on its own, arisen in all those properties that we discussed.
[SPEAKER_04]: Rather than automatically just sort of toppling over and further to get rid of it and replace it, or attend away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then that's pulling back and seeing it, okay, getting perspective.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, learning how to concurrently attend to whatever has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, that's... yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, is it possible to go too far in the other way?
[SPEAKER_03]: Would you then end up mystifying the womb?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, no, because you would be unconcurrently attending that.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can't have too much of a balance.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, yeah, this is what I was trying to get to, but could it be unbalanced in the opposite way towards sensuality?
[SPEAKER_03]: What would that be?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, yeah, yeah, because the opposite way would just become another thing in front of you.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's when I say, like, oh, okay, so this is my experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the background to it is this enduring feeling that now you made into a foreground by overly attending to it, by not seeing it as a background to what's in front, but by turning your attention to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why, again, it won't be the yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So you can't have too much of yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the same sense, you can't have too much of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, you counted too much.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, the balance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, this balance is too good.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's not right.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if there is no balance, means there is no yonismo nisikāra.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Means, whatever direction there was a relative counterweight, you just made into a new weight, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you overdo it...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, it doesn't matter in which direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Doesn't matter, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: In which direction you overdo it, you end up stuck, standing in front of you, unbalanced.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: You'll be hindered.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you will... because actually you cannot get out.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_04]: All you can see is, with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the balance.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the way out.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the relinquishing of ownership.
[SPEAKER_04]: If that sight, that recognition, that knowledge is fully developed and unperturbable, and the balance cannot be lost.